<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter xml:id="chapter.concepts"
	 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
     xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
     xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
     xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
     xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
     xmlns:mathml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">

	<title>Concepts</title>
	<para>This section tries to explain some of the basic concepts of the calendar.</para>
	
	<section xml:id="chapter.concepts.eventindex">
		<title>Event Index</title>
		<para>
			<productname>Calendar Base</productname> introduced something called <emphasis>New Recurring Event Model</emphasis>.
			This concept was borrowed and applied to all of <productname>cz_simple_cal</productname> events by default. The index is automatically updated if you modify
			an event. So depending on how many recurrances and exceptions you've set up, storing might take a while longer.
		</para>
		<note>
			The extension is smart enough to notify if you changed some values that actually require indexing to run again.
			So if you only change the title or a description, no indexing is done.
		</note>
		<note>
			<para>You can use the <productname>scheduler</productname> extension to re-index all your events. This 
			should be done if you updated Exceptions that are applied to multiple Events, moved records around or if you 
			changed the <code>recurrenceEnd</code> setting. The <productname>scheduler</productname> is a core extension
			and shipped with <productname>TYPO3</productname>, but you might have to install it in the extension manager.
			</para>
		</note>
		
		<para>
			Due to the indexing of events you usually deal with <link linkend="glossary.eventindex">EventIndices</link> in your
			templates. But the objects are smart enough to tunnel unknown methods to the <link linkend="glossary.eventindex">Event</link>
			they belong to. So you can work with <literal>EventIndices</literal> as if they were Events.   
		</para>
	</section>
	
	<section xml:id="chapter.concepts.fake-actions">
		<title>Fake Actions</title>
		<para>
			To make the extension as flexible as possible you can add <link linkend="glossary.fake-actions">fake actions</link>
			to the controllers in your TypoScript.
		</para>
		<para>
			Fake Actions are actions you can add to a Controller solely through TypoScript.
		</para>
		<para>See <link linkend="chapter.howto.add-fake-action">HowTo: Add a fake action</link> to learn - guess what - how to add a fake action.</para>
	</section>
	
	<section xml:id="chapter.concepts.date-type">
		<title>The type <literal>date</literal></title>
		<para>
			This type is quite heavily used in the extension. It allowes for a very flexible and simple calculation of dates
			and times. It is based on the english language and international date and time formats.
		</para>
		<para>
			The recommended way of setting a fixed day and time is the <literal>YYYY-MM-DD (HH:MM:SS[T]?)?</literal> syntax, but
			there are also different valid syntaxes:
		</para>
		<example>
			<title>Examples of valid dates and times</title>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para><userinput>2009-02-13</userinput></para></listitem>
				<listitem><para><userinput>2009-02-13 23:31:30</userinput></para></listitem>
				<listitem><para><userinput>2009-02-13 23:31:30UTC</userinput></para></listitem>
				<listitem><para><userinput>13.2.09 23.31.30+00:00</userinput></para></listitem>
				<listitem><para><userinput>February 13th, 2009 11 pm</userinput></para></listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</example>
		<note><para>Note that you can't use localized month names here.</para></note>
		<para>Additionally you can use relative dates and chaining of different relative dates.</para>
		<example>
			<title>Examples of valid relative dates</title>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para><userinput>yesterday</userinput></para></listitem>
				<listitem><para><userinput>last monday</userinput></para></listitem>
				<listitem><para><userinput>+1 month -1 day</userinput></para></listitem>
				<listitem><para><userinput>first day this month|monday this week</userinput></para></listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</example>
		<para>See <link linkend="appendix.date">the appendix for the complete syntax.</link></para>
	</section>
</chapter>