<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter xml:id="chapter.faq"
	 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
     xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
     xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
     xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
     xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
     xmlns:mathml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">

	<title>FAQs</title>
	
	<qandaset>
		<qandaentry>
			<question>
				<para>Why isn't [name any feature here] implemented?</para>
			</question>
			<answer>
				<para>Most likely because no one has needed it yet.</para>
				<para>
					Following the <emphasis>YAGNI</emphasis> (= &quot;You Ain't Gonna Need It&quot;) principle of programming,
					features are implemented as soon as they are needed. If you miss a feature, it might be because no one has
					programmed or at least requested it.
				</para>
				<para>
					The best way to get your feature added is by opening a ticket, doing the coding and submitting your work.<sbr/>
					If you are not a coder please submit a feature request to the bugtracker. If you find, someone else has already
					requested that feature, please comment on it and state that you'd like to have that feature, too. This way
					we can easily decide which are the most desired features.<sbr/>
					And last but not least you could consider sponsoring the development of a feature. Get in touch with us if you
					wish to do so.
				</para>
			</answer>
		</qandaentry>
		<qandaentry>
			<question>
				<para>I'm a programmer, how can I dive into the code?</para>
			</question>
			<answer>
				<para>
					You should be familiar with <productname>Extbase</productname> and <productname>Fluid</productname>.
					The source code itself is documented inline, so there should be a brief explanation on what each class and 
					method is used for. Read the according section to understand the <link linkend="chapter.administration.concepts">
					basic concepts and philosophies of the extension</link>.
				</para>
				<para>
					If you have any difficulties on understanding the code, you can contact the developer through the email-adressen
					given in <productname>TYPO3 Forge</productname>. 
				</para>
			</answer>
		</qandaentry>
	</qandaset>
	
</chapter>