<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter xml:id="chapter.howto"
	 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
     xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
     xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
     xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
     xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
     xmlns:mathml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">

	<title>HowTo's</title>

	<section xml:id="chapter.howto.add-fake-action">
		<title>Add a fake action</title>
		
		<para>
			Adding a fake action is pretty simple and can be done only using TypoScript. Let's say we want to add a view that
			displays the event that has recently finished. We'll call this action <literal>recent</literal>.
		</para>
		
		<procedure>
			<step>
				<title>Choose a fitting real action</title>
				<para>
					In our example case this would be the <literal>listAction</literal>. <literal>ShowAction</literal> won't fit as 
					you don't know the id of the event to display in advance. Instead, we'll limit the list to display only one 
					event.
				</para>
			</step>
			<step>
				<title>Extend the TypoScript configuration</title>
				
				<note><para>All given TypoScript paths are relative to <code>plugin.tx_czsimplecal</code>. I am to lazy to
					add this to the path each time, and so should you. Use the curly brackets: <code>plugin.tx_czsimplecal{ //... }</code>
				</para></note>
				
				<para>
					The TypoScript settings already hold some action configurations. So we'll just copy the configuration for the 
					<literal>listAction</literal> in <code>settings.EventIndex.actions.list</code> to <code>settings.EventIndex.actions.recent</code>.
				</para>
				
				<para>The configureable options should be pretty obvious. But first we'll add <code>useAction = list</code> to the 
				actions configuration. This way the fake <literal>recentAction</literal> knows which real action to call.
				Now we can change the other configuration like this:
				</para>
				
				<programlisting>recent {
    useAction  = list
    startDate  = now -1 month
    endDate    = now

    maxEvents = 1
    orderBy   = end  
    order     = DESC
}</programlisting>
				<para>Guess what each of the configuration values is doing. ;) We select all events between now and one month ago,
				order them by their endtime and just pick the first one.</para>
			</step>
			
			<step>
				<title>Add the action to the allowed actions</title>
				<para>Just add the name of the action to the <code>allowedActions</code> in <code>settins.EventIndex</code>.</para>
			</step>
			
			<step>
				<title>Create a view</title>
				<para>
					Well, thats even simpler: Just copy the <literal>list.html</literal> template and rename it to
					<literal>recent.html</literal>. Do changes on the file if you like - removing the dayWrapper could be a good idea.
				</para>
			</step>
		
		</procedure>
		
		
	</section>
	
</chapter>