<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter xml:id="chapter.scheduler"
	 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
     xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
     xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
     xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
     xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
     xmlns:mathml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">

	<title>Scheduler</title>

	<section xml:id="chapter.scheduler.basics">
		<title>Understanding the index task</title>
		
		<para>
			The purpose of the index task is to create an index of all events as described in the
			<link linkend="chapter.concepts.eventindex">basic concepts</link>.
		</para>
		<para>
			But you usually don't have to run the scheduler permanently to keep the index up to date.
			The extension makes sure, that the index is up to date, when you create, edit, move or delete events.
		</para>
		<para>
			Some of the cases where you actually need to update the index include:
		</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					Events where not added through <productname>TYPO3</productname>s native forms.
				</para>
				<para>
					This might happen if you use any weired extension, that manipulates records on a
					database level or if you even manipulate the records on the database yourself. 
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					You have recurring events and use
					<link linkend="chapter.configuration.extconf"><literal>recurranceEnd</literal></link>
					with a relative date format.
				</para>
				<para>
					I would recommend this way as it keeps your database tables as small as possible and 
					you probably don't want recurring events to repeat until ten years from now.
					If you had limited <literal>recurranceEnd</literal> to <userinput>+1 year</userinput>
					you should update your index every once in a while as the event index will only have
					been created for one year from your last editing of the event. If you would not run the
					scheduler, your event would "disappear" one year after.
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		
		<para>
			So, to comprehend: You don't need to set up a scheduler task if you do not use recurring events
			or only use them with <literal>recurrance until</literal> for a short time.
		</para>
	</section>
	
	<section xml:id="chapter.scheduler.configuration">
		<title>index task configuration</title>
		<variablelist>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>minimum age for reindexing</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						An event will only be reindexed if it was indexed prior to the date given here.
					</para>
					<para>
						This field is of the <link linkend="appendix.date"><literal>date</literal> type</link>.
						So if you enter <userinput>-1 month</userinput> all the events will be re-indexed after one month.
					</para>
					<note>
						<para>
							Depending on how many events you have, the indexer might be to slow to index all events in 
							one run. So your scheduler should run more often than the value in this property, if you 
							can't ensure that your machine is capable of indexing all events at once.
						</para>
					</note>
					<para>
						If you leave this field empty the events that where indexed the longest time ago will be indexed.
						The process will run until all events where indexed or the script stops due to missing memory
						or time.
					</para>
					<note>
						<para>
							Needless to say it is not recommended to run this task every 5 minutes. But this comes
							in handy if you need to reindex your events manually.
						</para>
					</note>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
		</variablelist>
	</section>
	
</chapter>